# **Ankit** Ojha

#### MECHANICAL DESIGN ENGINEER

# **SUMMARY**

Product design engineer with 7+ years of automotive industry expertise.

Experience in innovative product design and development.

I'm currently employed as a senior design technician at SKF Engineering and Lubrication, where I work on passenger vehicle wheelends.

# SKILLS

- GD & T
- Vehicle Integration
- DFMEA
- VA / VE
- CREO PARAMETRIC

# **EXPERIENCE**

# Senior Design Technician

# SKF Engineering and Lubrication India Pvt. Ltd. Dec 2021 - Present

- New bearing selection and design for passenger car wheel end hub bearings (North America)
- Calculating bearing life and fit
- DFMEA revision for new and existing failures
- Optimization of design parameters (weight, friction, packaging, and manufacturing process)
- ECN administration and follow-up
- Data collection and cost estimation for new needs
- Production and proposal drawings
- Developing a technical inquiry paper to recommend the design of supplier parts such as seals, caps, and sensor carriers

# Senior Design Engineer

Onward Technologies Apr 2021 - Dec 2021

# **ELECTROMECHANICAL DESIGN AT CUMMINS INDIA**

- Design of electromechanical fixtures
- Component design, stack-up analysis, and Poka Yoke
- Follow-up with project stakeholders
- Creating a manufacturing drawing

# **ENGINE INSTALLATION DESIGN AT CNH INDIA**

- I created a 3D and 2D design for a sheet metal protection cover for the primary gasoline tank.
- Design of mounting structures and protective covers for gas tanks, external headlamps, and additional peripheral components
- Agriculture Tractor Integration
- Electric wire and gasoline hose routing
- Initial Validation and Fitment (DFS)
- Follow up with the component supplier.

• Creating manufacturing drawings.

# Senior Design Engineer

TATA Technologies Nov 2018 - Mar 2021

# • CLIENT NAME: MCFA, DESIGN AND DRAFTING OF FORKLIFT SYSTEM:

- Generated CAD models, assemblies, and drawings (part, assembly, and installation) for forklift systems. While applying G.D. and T. principles.
- Created sheet metal 3D model parts, drawings, and assemblies of the dashboard, floor, and similar other components of the forklift.
- Created metal and hose pipe routing for hydraulic and steering systems.
- Created skeleton modeling for assembly-level designs by utilizing the top-down and bottom-up approaches.
- Create generic CAD models by using the Creo Family Table option.
- Efficiently drafted markup drawings for many parts and assemblies.
- Prepared a bill of materials and self-QCed all drawings and assemblies.
- Used Windchill PDM for check-in and check-out of CAD and other documents.
- New part creation, WT creation, renaming of parts, assembly, and drawing Addition of BOM structure, related CAD model or drawing, and exchange of documents

# CLIENT NAME: TATA STEEL, DESIGN AND DRAFTING OF STEEL MANUFACTURING PLANT PARTS AND ASSEMBLIES:

- Created 3D models and 2D sketches in parametric from scratch conditions.
- Used top-down and bottom-up approaches for skeleton modeling.
- Provided design support by modeling 3D models and 2D drafting parts and assemblies with 3D annotation.
- Provided welding symbols on assemblies according to the manufacturing process.
- I did self-QC for drawings and assemblies for error-less delivery.
- Designed pipe routing models by using piping tools.
- Prepared the bill of materials.

# CLIENT NAME: Tata Motors, DESIGN AND DRAFTING OF FRONT AXLE AND STEERING SYSTEMS:

- Created 3D models 2D drafting of parts and assemblies Designed pipe models by using piping tools.
- created an envelope in CAD through the mechanisms of the front axle and steering to find fouling with other aggregates.
- Package the front axle, steering, wheel rim, tire, and brakes to check for fouling and develop new ideas for new product development.
- o completed the DML (Design Modification List) process for design release.
- completed the DR (Design Release) migration process as per requirement.
- efficient use of drafting, detailing, and section with B.O.M., G.D. & T., and machining symbol skills.
- verified part and assembly design by using JT of Team Center software.
- Created 4D documents (DFA, DFM, DFS, and DFMEA) for parts and assemblies.
- DFMEA analysis to prevent failure. Interacted with the supplier for design changes, modifications, or release.
- o cross-functional team meeting with a VI member (the vehicle design owner).
- Design support for other team members of the chassis system

#### Junior Manager

VE Commercial Vehicle Ltd. Feb 2017 - Nov 2018

# • DESIGN AND DRAFTING OF THE FRONT AXLE, STEERING, AND REAR WHEEL END:

- 3D modeling and drafting of the front axle and steering components
- Vehicle level layout verification "Fitment"
- E-BOM and M-BOM creation
- Installation and routing
- Parts catalog creation for spares
- Envelope design creation of the front axle and steering mechanism
- Check sheet preparation as per CMVR rules to release the front axle design.

- Follow up with stakeholders and suppliers to meet deliverables.
- Interacted with suppliers by visiting their firm to discuss RTS points for better manufacturability on new design releases.
- 3D modeling and drafting of the front axle and steering components
- Vehicle level layout verification "Fitment"
- E-BOM and M-BOM creation
- Installation and routing
- Parts catalog creation for spares
- Envelope design creation of the front axle and steering mechanism
- Check sheet preparation as per CMVR rules to release the front axle design.
- Follow up with stakeholders and suppliers to meet deliverables.
- Interacted with suppliers by visiting their firm to discuss RTS points for better manufacturability on new design releases.

# Trainee

KPIT Technologies Jul 2015 - Jan 2017

# CLIENT NAME: HEIL TRAILER, SUPPORT FOR THE DESIGN AND DRAFTING OF A SEMI-TTRAILER (PORTABLE WATER TANKER)

- Using parametric sketch modeling, I created sheet metal pieces.
- 3D models and 2D drawings of parts and assemblies were created.
- Using a 2D layout, I created solid modeling.
- At the novice level, I learned Creo, AutoCAD, Solid Works, Unigraphics, and PDM.
- Under the supervision of the senior designer, I learned and practiced drafting, detailing, and sectioning alongside B.O.M., G.D., and T.
- For drawing and modeling, I created a Q.C. checklist.

# CLIENT NAME: EATON, IMDS, SUPPORT FOR QUALITY ENSUREMENT

- The designers' Q.C. checklist was validated.
- I discovered that the NCs were done by designers.
- Solved Designers and teams have problems while designing.
- Participating in designer-client conference calls for project-related questions
- The RCA approach was used to resolve projects that were stalled.

# **EDUCATION**

Diploma in Tool and Die making, Mechanical Engineering NTTF (Nettur Technical Training Foundation) *Jul 2012 - Jun 2015* I graduated with an aggregate of 70%.

# Matriculation

Shogra High School 2012

I graduated with an aggregate of 78%.

# **LANGUAGES**

Hindi	Kannada	$\bullet \bullet \bullet \circ \circ$
English		